A Guide to the Colonel William Christian Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1935-1990s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Special Collections, Virginia Tech
Colonel William Christian Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records, 1935-1990s
Special Collections, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, Va.
Ms2014-013
0.5 cu. ft. 1 box
The Colonel William Christian Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records contain administrative papers, memorabilia, documents relating to community work, and correspondence from the now disbanded Christiansburg, VA, chapter. Papers date from the mid 1930s to the 1990s.
Daughters of the American Revolution. Colonel William Christian Chapter. (Christiansburg, Va.)
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Acquisition Information
This collection was donated to Special Collections in 2014.
Administrative History
Founded in Washington, D. C. in 1890, the National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution arose from a desire on the part of women to participate more fully in an upsurge of patriotism during the late nineteenth century. A volunteer service organization, the DAR's mission objectives involve patriotism, preservation of American history, and education. With membership restricted to women who can prove a direct descent from a participant in the American Revolution, the DAR by 2004 encompassed approximately 170,000 members in nearly 2,300 chapters.
The Colonel William Christian Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution was the Christiansburg Chapter of the NSDAR. The chapter was established in 1935 and stayed active throughout the rest of the twentieth century before being disbanded.
Scope and Content
The collection contains administrative materials from the organization, programs and mementos from chapter and regional events, information about DAR memorials and markers, as well as articles featuring information about the Christiansburg Chapter.
Arrangement
The records in this collection are organized into ten series, based on topics and subjects, and arranged alphabetically by title. The collection includes Series I: Administrative Materials, Series II: Awards, Series III: Brochures and Pamphlets, Series IV: Christiansburg DAR Chapter History, Series V: Correspondence, Series VI: Markers and Memorials, Series VII: Memorials and Funerals, Series VIII: Publications, Series IX: Special Events and Meetings, and Series X: Yearbooks and Photographs. Within each series, folders are in alphabetical order by title.
Adjunct Descriptive Data
Related Materials
Alleghany Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records. Finding aid available online.
Floyd Courthouse Chapter, National Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution Records. Finding aid available online.
Index Terms
Corporate Names:
Daughters of the American Revolution. Colonel William Christian Chapter. (Christiansburg, Va.)
Georgraphical Names:
Christiansburg (Va.)
Subjects:
Home economics; Hotel Roanoke; Local/Regional History and Appalachian South; Montgomery County (Va.)
Contents List
- Series I: Administrative Materials
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Minutes (Box-folder 1-10)
  - NSDAR "Application Papers: Instructions for Their Preparation " (1985) (Box-folder 1-45)
  - NSDAR "General Information for Prospective Members" (1967) (Box-folder 1-47)
  - NSDAR "Information for Chapter Registrars" (Box-folder 1-48)
  - NSDAR Membership Guidebook Revised Ed. (1965) (Box-folder 1-62)
  - NSDAR "Requirements for and Preparation of Applications Papers" (Box-folder 1-50)
  - Report of the Treasurer General of National Society of the DAR (1972) (Box-folder 1-53)
  - State Officers Club VA DAR (1968) (Box-folder 1-55)
- Series II: Awards
  - NSDAR Certificate for Participation in the Independence Jubilee Project (Box-folder 1-46)
- Series III: Brochures and Pamphlets
  - Brochures for the Kate Duncan Smith DAR School, Grant, Alabama (Box-folder 1-3)
  - Brochure for the Tamasee DAR School, Tamasee, SC (Box-folder 1-5)
  - Christiansburg Self-Guided Historic Tour (Box-folder 1-18)
  - "The Flag Code" (Box-folder 1-29)
  - VA Catalogue of Historical Papers (1942) (Box-folder 1-57)
  - "Your Rights Under the Constitution" (Box-folder 1-42)
- Series IV: Christiansburg DAR Chapter History
  - DAR Chapter Dates to '35 (Box-folder 1-21)
  - The Life Story of Colonel William Christian by Redmond Ira Roop (Box-folder 1-37)
  - Mrs. A.O. Salmon's Frozen Fruitcake Recipe (Box-folder 1-39)
  - Tenth Anniversary of Christiansburg DAR History of the Chapter (January 26, 1945) (Box-folder 1-56)
- Series V: Correspondence
  - Article about the Christiansburg DAR's 40th Anniversary and Letter to Mrs. Evelyn Sutherland Regarding the Success of the Event, c. 1975 (Box-folder 1-1)
  - Letter from the Christiansburg NSDAR to Mayor E.P. Buckland Regarding Montgomery County Courthouse, February 25, 1975 (Box-folder 1-33)
  - Letter from Mrs. Minichan to Mrs. Pack, December 3, 1978 (Box-folder 1-34)
  - Letter to Mrs. Pack from M.W. Fishwick at VA Tech Dept. of Performing Arts and Communications, September 1, 1978 (Box-folder 1-35)
  - Letter to Mrs. Pack from Nathan Einhorn at the Library of Congress, October 29, 1982 (Box-folder 1-36)
  - Note from Mary Foley, May 1977 (Box-folder 1-44)
- Series VI: Markers and Memorials
  - "Dedication of Marker at the Grave of a Revolutionary War Patriot" (Box-folder 1-23)
  - Dedication of Marker Honoring John Lester, May 24, 1969 (Box-folder 1-24)
  - Dedication of Marker Honoring John Price Sr. and John Price Jr., October 19, 1969 (Box-folder 1-25)
  - "A Historic Prayer for Our Land" (Box-folder 1-32)
- Series VII: Memorials and Funerals for NSDAR Members and Their Families
  - Funeral and Memorial Programs, Cards from Families of Deceased DAR Members, and Newspaper Obituaries (Box-folder 1-30)
  - Grave side Service of William Shelbourne Roop (Box-folder 1-31)
- Series VIII: Publications
  - Bicentennial Herald, April, 18-22, 1977 (Box-folder 1-2)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Newspaper Articles (Box-folder 1-11)
  - The Congress Herald, April 19-23, 1976 (Box-folder 1-19)
  - The Congress Herald, April 18-22, 1977 (Box-folder 1-20)
  - DAR Magazine, January 1981 (Box-folder 1-22)
  - Newspaper Article About the Christiansburg DAR November 1974 Meeting Attached to a Photocopy of a Letter Written by William Christian (Box-folder 1-43)
- Series IX: Special Events and Meetings
  - Chaplain General's Pilgrimage Memo, April 1977 (Box-folder 1-6)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Chapter Diamond Jubilee Program and Menu, c. 1965 (Box-folder 1-7)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Chapter Fortieth Birthday Invitation, April 1985 (Box-folder 1-8)
  - District VII Virginia Society DAR Tenth Annual Meeting, September 21, 1966 (Box-folder 1-26)
  - District VII VA Society DAR Twelfth Annual Meeting, September 25, 1968 (Box-folder 1-27)
  - District VII Virginia Society DAR Thirteenth Annual Meeting, September 10, 1969 (Box-folder 1-28)
  - Lord's Day Liturgy, Washington Cathedral (Box-folder 1-38)
  - The New Jersey Room Information Packet-Bicentennial Commemoration of the Battle of Red Bank, October 19, 1975 (Box-folder 1-40)
  - New Years Night Open House Guest List, 1951 (Box-folder 1-41)
  - NSDAR Ribbons (Box-folder 1-51)
  - President General's Reception Room Information Sheet (Box-folder 1-52)
  - Seventy-Sixth State Conference VA DAR, March 1972 (Box-folder 1-54)
  - VA DAR Fifteenth Annual Meeting Memo (Box-folder 1-58)
  - VA DAR Forty-First Annual Meeting District VII Program, September 17, 1997 (Box-folder 1-59)
  - VA DAR Forty-Second Annual Meeting District VII Program, September 23, 1998 (Box-folder 1-60)
  - VA DAR Luncheon Eighty-Sixth Continental Congress, April 19, 1977 (Box-folder 1-61)
  - VA Society of the Daughters of the American Revolution One Hundreth State Conference, March 15, 1996 (Box-folder 1-62)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yorktown Visit (Box-folder 1-17)
- Series X: Yearbooks and Photographs
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Chapter Photographs, 1976 (Box-folder 1-9)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yearbook, 1955-1969 (Box-folder 1-12)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yearbook, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 1-13)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yearbook, 1975-1980 (Box-folder 1-14)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yearbook, 1980-1986 (Box-folder 1-15)
  - Christiansburg NSDAR Yearbook, 1986-1998 (Box-folder 1-16)
  - The Women's Club of Christiansburg Yearbook, 1983-1984 (Box-folder 1-63)